[Music]
now friends I know we're in trying times
and so I thought to myself what can I do
what would be one thing that unifies us
all all people around the world what's
one thing we have in common and it
brings us together and the answer hit me
after dinner one night
clearly it's 40 no one thinks farting is
it funny we all do it and we all love it
we can do it at any place any location
anywhere is fine for some party if
anything we're gonna get accomplished
today I don't know if you learn anything
but we're gonna spend an hour or more on
this topic and by girl you should at
least have some fun party information
and I know I'll make my wife Natasha so
so proud this is what I spent a week
working on that I couldn't help watch
the children with because I was making a
fourth video and not a short one an hour
long fart video so let's dive right into
it now of course I will talk about
farting today but really here's what I'm
gonna hit why you fart the basics of
digestion what FOB mats are starches
resistant starches soluble and insoluble
fiber common causes of GI distress
probiotics and prebiotics gut microbiome
digestive enzymes sugar protein bar
farts use sugar and sweetener
substitutes beans cabbage broccoli etc
inulin sorbitol and rocket fuel what the
hell fermentation non starchy
polysaccharides gut inflammation Crohn's
disease in IBS irritable bowel syndrome
that is how much fiber to eat when white
rice beats brown rice fecal transplants
poop in a pill and finally oatmeal and
cold pasta are you ready friends let's
go okay so what you may have realized is
that of all the foods you eat
carbohydrates proteins and fats actually
the vast majority of your gas comes from
carbohydrates even though you eat like
eggs in New York and your farts smell
like eggs it's probably not the cause
protein and fat generally don't
especially fat really don't contribute
to gas now if you eat it a boatload of
fat you're gonna get really watery or
sorry
really oily stool so it'll slide right
out but it really won't cause a lot of
gas so really understand why
carbohydrates give you so much
flatulence it's because of this so let's
break down what they are and how they
operate so the three real categories of
carbohydrates are sugars starches and
fiber and in other separate videos one
called what are carbohydrates
specifically I break down each of these
subcategories what it means to be mono
and I poly and holy ghost a cried the
cetera but for now you'll just have to
trust me so here's what typically
happens your human anatomy is your
stomach is actually way up here even
though we grab our stomach and stuff
down there it's actually really high
just below our liver your stomach feeds
into what are called the small
intestines and there's three kind of
separate parts of those but we'll ignore
that for now the small intestines then
feed into the larger intestines and
that's also synonymous with the colon
alright so same sort of thing all right
now typically what happens if you've got
enzymes all throughout that system but
especially in the small intestines and
any foods that are broken down or need
to get digested from those enzymes if
they're introduced that you have
generally no problems no gaseous
emissions from these things and so sugar
and starches for the most part the ones
that are purple coated here the ones
that are be easily digested in the SI or
small intestines you have no issues so
these things generally don't cause gas
or problems in fact any sugar or starch
and a good example of this is rice if
they're able to be digested in the small
intestines they almost surely won't give
you much gaps it's the things that have
to move past the small intestines that
cause you problems and so what are those
well the first example would be the
types of sugars or the the sugars that
need to be rapidly fermented in the
large a distance so sugars hit your
stomach and this is again only some
types of sugars because some are easily
digestible but these ones I hit your
stomach and they actually need a
different enzyme in that little Pacman
line so they get there and the pac-man
doesn't work on them and so they
continue to go through undigested or non
digested they get to the large
intestines and now they meet up with a
whole bunch of bacteria and these
bacteria do
have the enzymes necessary to break down
these special types of sugars and so
what they do is is they they actually go
through what's called rapid fermentation
and you know really the gist of what
fermentation means but it's exactly what
you think and so these these micro
bacteria ferment the the sugar in that
larger intestine and a classic example
of that is what I call a gal so a gala
is the enzyme responsible or needed to
break down raffinose which we'll cover
in a second it's particularly gnarly and
causes a whole bunch of your gaseous
problems we don't have a gal in our
smaller intestines so raffinose is
really hard to digest there but by the
time we get to our larger intestines
it's on those bacteria and they have it
and there's a ton of these different
enzymes to really cover your bases it's
you're probably caught up talking a
couple of dozen enzymes or more to get
all the foods but I put up a gal just
because again it's really common in
raffinose is so gnarly in our system as
a result of any of these bacteria
nonetheless so anytime there's
fermentation happening in the large
intestines it's gonna result in kicking
out what are called short chain fatty
acids and I'll talk about what these
aren't later if you're into ketosis or
using different shorter fats you may
have been familiar with short chain
fatty acids as a byproduct of this
fermentation or metabolism in other
words it's kind of like the bacteria
farts it's gas and that causes exactly
what you think it's gonna cause in you
so if you have a bunch of these foods
you're gonna have a bunch of these
processes going on and you're gonna of
course have a bunch of gas buildup so
these foods that need to be rapidly
fermented in larger intestines are put
together in an acronym that we call
FODMAPs and I'll explain you what those
are in a second okay now outside of that
some starches like I said rice and some
other ones our easily bananas are easily
digested in the small intestines but the
subcategory of starches that are not
they actually have to go to large
intestine and they're generally not
rapidly fermented but they can be slowly
fermented and so they're not fond mats
but they are what we call resistant
starches and the name is actually
perfect here right they're called that
because they are starches that are
resistant to digestion so they need
different enzymes and the
pac-man you get the idea right they go
to large intestines and they tend to
cause some gaseous disruption great
example this our bananas and we'll get
this later but it's you don't want to
just go memorizing foods here because
it's not only the foods that can alter
what happens in digestion but it's also
the preparation method so different ways
of cooking slicing cutting etc all can
change whether something is a fodmap or
not a fob map or a resistance starch or
a normal starch and a good example that
of bananas so if you take a really ripe
yellow banana almost surely it'll be
well the majority of it will be
processed perfectly fine in the smaller
intestines so it is starch and sugar but
it's no problem it's it's a sugar a and
search a in this picture however if you
were to take a green banana a green
banana is actually hasn't been fully
converted over into and if fructose and
glucose and maybe the sucrose yet and so
it actually acts like a resistance
starch and so a green banana may give
you a bunch of gas but a yellow banana
wouldn't okay great example there and
we'll talk more about resistant starches
later then there's also just general
fiber so there's other fibers that are
fermented sometimes rapid sometimes
slowly in our intestines and those are
gonna contribute as well and we'll have
a whole section on fiber when they get
there and then our final category of
things I could contribute are underneath
the fiber category or what I call NSPS
which are non starchy polysaccharides
these are like cellulose and pectin and
depend potentially waxes and things like
that and those will actually make their
way through the entire digestive system
and you'll basically defecate those out
without ever having process them so do
be careful as you're reading around this
topic because you'll see things like say
resistant starches are quote-unquote not
digested by humans we don't have the
enzymes to break them down it's not
totally true what they usually mean by
that is we don't have those enzymes in
the small intestines okay so be really
careful when you read that they skip
that part you're like oh I guess we
humans can't digest some polysaccharide
well no you just can't digest it in the
stomach and small intestines you
let the bacteria which is like another
species do it but that's still in your
body all right but there are some like I
said the NSPS that are truly just never
digested and will go all the way through
and come out the back end if you've ever
seen a gorilla at a zoo who poops picks
its own food up and pulls the strings
right like the fibers right back out of
it meets it again you'll know that this
is very much the case if you ever seen
corn in your poop all right things can
get through your entire digestive system
whatever without being ever broken down
okay so let's jump into these spot mats
first okay now you can see what the
acronym stands for here but I throw the
word rapidly in front of it because
really what we're talking about are
things that are rapidly fermentable
oligo mono or oligo dye and
monosaccharides as well as polyols and
I'll talk about those in a second but
let's go through them one by one so the
only go saccharides which means they
have anywhere between two to eight
saccharides put together so mono mean
one only goes to two eight right uh here
monosaccharides glucose fructose and
galactose okay well the two most common
examples are raffinose and fructose and
from within fractions the most common
and most important when you should know
is come in human not in solin in Ulan
okay now in so most of the ins
here i'm talking about are actually any
other specific but you can get fructose
from anything on that list you see there
jicama basically any grass right so we
tries things like that barley are going
to contain a lot of fructose and a lot
of inulin right now what's weird about
this as I've mentioned rice is able to
be digested in smaller intestines and
that's why the reason is because it
actually doesn't contain fuckton so it
doesn't give you gut disruptions it's
not a fun this is why people love rice
is the most easily digested starch
without question right no problems gets
in fast and causes no stomach issues
which is really helpful when you're
trying to be in a hyper caloric diet
you're trying to eat a lot of food a lot
of food you don't want to just be
bloated out to here all day garlic
onions other things and jicama all
contain a lot of fructose a lot of
inulin
now in eelain's particularly cool back
up
things in general are does a fancy name
is kind of a polymer here is it's a
fructose or fructose plus sucrose right
and so only about 10% as sweet as
sucrose so no one would ever take a bite
of we'd be like ooh super sweet even
though you know it's full carbohydrates
and it's a lot of sugar because it's not
super sweet and generally when we find
this especially as a dietary supplement
it's made from chicory root that's what
we gonna which we're gonna make the vast
majority of our enuine it's technically
a soluble fiber and so it actually
functions as a prebiotic which we'll
talk about later but a prebiotic
basically means it feeds your gut
bacteria which is exactly what we talked
about because it is soluble you can
break it down or you can soluble eyes
with water and typically these
ins are old ago saccharides but they're
anywhere between 170 fructose units and
so they can be oligo saccharides or
polysaccharides now another fun fact
about fractions and inulin especially is
they kind of work like in roots and
rhizomes anyways they're used to store
the kind of polysaccharide and so
they're almost used as an anti-freeze
which is really awesome so plants have
these Ruxin's a lot because they can go
back and forth between traditional
starch and this inulin function and when
it gets really cold and freezes if they
convert over to a frog dinner in Ulan
then they don't actually die in and
break up so it's a really cool
by-product so the if you're looking at
like foods that have England versus
foods that have traditional starch the
roots and rhizomes that can't make the
starches are going to make the
vice-versa so it's a really cool system
they have to kind of use whatever is
most effective at the time okay now any
'la is also cool you may have heard of
it if you've ever had any work with a
nephrologist or any having kidney issues
because of the way that it actually goes
through the kidneys it's not using
absorbed it can actually use those or
measure for what's called GFR or
globular filtration rate in other words
it can tell you how your kidneys
function it's just really really awesome
because like how the hell does this pod
Matt actually telling about my kidneys
but that's some way you can look into
that more on your own but it's a pretty
cool way to use so you'll you'll see it
a lot in blood work but you're like well
why did I care about my gesture they
don't care about your digestion
looking at your kidneys if they murdered
anyone okay so let's move on oh yeah
also by the way I kind of mentioned this
but to be clear inland is by far the
most common fiber additive in food so if
you've ever had any like cereal with
added fiber or anything like that a
protein bar that add fiber almost always
they're using chicory root and getting
in Ulan from that and putting it in so
in fact so much so it's almost
synonymous if you have anything with
added fiber just assume it's in Ulan
what they're putting in there okay now
under raffinose I said this is probably
the biggest problem area of all the fog
masses it's very very common it causes
some significant issues you find it in
beans cabbage and broccoli right there's
no one out here is confused that you've
had this effect that we have an amazing
song that I've already taught my not
even two-year-old daughter about beans
and it being a magical fruit right and
so I'll talk a little bit more about
that later but raffinose is a big big
player in this equation it's actually
the base for sucralose a lot of the time
so you can use it manufacturing wise it
super low stable sugar right so you can
use raffles to get that as the base and
then make it from there they have to add
some sweeter sugar into it because
raffinose the self is actually not
particularly sweet even though the fact
that it is I trisaccharide so I can only
go is Socrates anywhere between a 2 and
10 monosaccharides together in this
particularly this case it's tri so it's
3 it is 1 fructose 1 glucose and
galactose so it's pretty cool there it's
the only one I think that has all three
like that other fun stuff about
raffinose it's the second most abundant
soluble carbohydrate in nature mine
sucrose of course so soup roast is that
disaccharide table sugar it's glucose
and fructose together really common in
actual cells raffinose it's everywhere
so you'll find it in everything but
again as I mentioned it's not sweet it's
only about as 10% of sweet as sucrose
and that's typically because galactose
is not sweet even though it is the most
base sugar out there right two
monosaccharides
it's not incredibly sweet and so again
no one would confuse eating a Brussels
sprout or asparagus or beans and being
like I mean this is so sweet
despite the fact that it you know I'm
saying
moving on then the next two categories
are very very short so disaccharides at
monosaccharides the the primary issue
disaccharide causing potential problems
is lactose you know where you get
lactose from now if you don't have
issues with lactose like me then this is
not really going to contribute to your
problems if you do like my wife then I
don't need to explain to you even if
you're not quote-unquote lactose
intolerant if you just lactose
insensitive this could have problems and
the primary issue with people who are
lactose intolerant they get gassing and
this is why right in fact Lexi says that
that's that enzyme I talked about right
for whatever reason Natasha doesn't have
much of it and her small intestines I do
so it doesn't digest well there it goes
to her large intestines it gets
fermented and boom she gets gas right so
a different enzyme that now a gal like
you need raffinose different one for
lactose right like this does the same
thing it's fruit right so oddly enough
some people get gas from fruit if it has
too much fructose in it I put those fats
or of course any candy sweet product etc
that is made with high fructose corn
syrup could have the same issue albeit
it's much more difficult right straight
fructose from fruit is the other so now
let's move on to our last chord category
which of these polygons now these are
generally what we would call sugar
alcohols or at least sugar alcohols are
the most important poly poly all that we
care about in this discussion and these
are the explanation for things like
protein bar farts or even like health
bar farts if you will and so people
think oh my god I had all these up look
juicy if you've ever been to I know I
spent many years going to the Arnold
Classic and you walk around and it's
just a smash of people with cutoff
shirts and Everywhere's giving out free
protein shakes and protein bars and the
place smells horrific right and we're
always like cause too much protein well
it's not it's probably the sugar
alcohols in the protein bars and these
are special because they're not always
reported or known as causing they're the
source of calories in food additives but
they're very very very common so like I
said they they're actually do have
calories but they're under the threshold
of what people have to report and so
they're typically listed as zero calorie
on food items and that's because like I
said they're not digested well and so
instead of giving you four calories per
gram they typically give you somewhere
between two and three calories per gram
and so a quarter to a half of it gets
all the way through the digestive system
without being broken down so they're
lower in calories that way and if you
give somebody really high concentrations
like 20 grams or more maybe up to 40 or
more these can be used in laxatives in
fact some of these are MIT used in
laxative products which I'll talk about
in a second right but you don't
necessarily have to worry about these
like as far as something causing real
problems in your stomach if you're
eating them in a very moderate amount so
in a protein bar here or there you're
fine if you eat 12 protein bars a day
you'll start getting close to that 20
grams of actual sugar alcohols so
there's more there's four of these
primary ones I want to discuss sorbitol
mannitol xylitol and multi at all but
for the most part they're not the most
possible directly these things are used
as food additives
artificial sweeteners and sugar
substitutes or combinations on them and
that's the primary thing people
associate sugar alcohols with now the
thing about them is what makes them a
sugar alcohol is they're less sweet then
what what are called your high intensity
sweeteners so your aspartame your
saccharine your sucralose typically
again sugar alcohols are less sweet than
sucrose where if you look at these high
intensity sweeteners they're anywhere
between two and six hundred times
sweeter than sucrose so do not confuse
these sugar alcohols with aspartame or
saccharin of sucralose they're literally
hundreds of times less sweet okay so
what are they used for and what we do
with them first one Malta's all over
there it's hydrogenated corn this is
where we get it from as malted so you
actually can take malts so it's a
disaccharide right and you melt the corn
and then you can hydrogenate it and you
can get this multi tal that's why it's
called that now multi tall stuff is is
actually pretty sweet it's about 90% as
sucrose but not all the way the next one
mannitol that's primarily made from
seaweed which again it's crazy you're
gonna take that extract it out and get
from there it's insanely common in
nature in fact maybe even the most
common one of these it's everywhere and
people use it for fun things like eye
medicine and even diuretics so it's used
in a whole bunch of applications xylitol
xylitol excuse me is another one that
you're very likely to be familiar with
it's in pumpkins plums cauliflower
strawberries etc and a bunch of
different things like that and it
actually is almost as sweet basically as
sweet as sucrose and so because of that
it's actually much sweeter than sorbitol
and manny now this is one of the reasons
why you've heard of it because it is
used a lot because it is so sweet it has
some other particular fun facts facts
about it though it's made from birch
trees and there's also a plant fiber
called xylene which is where they stole
the xylitol name from but about 50 to 75
percent of it has to be fermented and so
you can see Wow super sweet but if it
has to be fermented and it also has to
be metabolized in the liver and so
because of this it has sort of a hot and
cold excitation level of females some
people love so manufacturers loved using
their food for obvious reasons but it
tends to give some people some real real
problems all right it is easier to
digest though than manny and Sorbo so
that's another benefit of it there and
then finally our last one of store
battle and this is by you've almost
surely heard of this anyone who's spent
any time trying to learn about nutrition
has come across this so it's an apples
pears peaches and particularly print in
fact this is the reason why they
recommend prunes for constipation and
things land regularity if you will is
because it has so much sorbitol in it
now interesting mannitol sorbitol are
actually isomers of each other so if
you're a chemistry person you can even
know what that means
you may think that's pretty cool but
yeah nice of isomers of each other super
tall is really really important because
even though it's only about sixty
percent as sweet as sucrose you can make
it easily from potato starch so you can
see how you can go from there to the
other one it's also used in things like
e.coli
identification and so the the nasty type
of e.coli think is how this works
doesn't or can't digest it very well but
other types can so if you put it in
there it doesn't digest you know that
you have the pathogen version of e.coli
and i guess most bacteria can't for
whatever reason do it as well and so for
these reasons sorbitol is used in
cosmetics to pace etc and in fact all of
these polygons are used in everything
all of your artificial sweeteners
sugar-free gum so I shared a free gum
gives a lot of people gas hard candies
especially through sugar free or lower
sugar these things were probably used
and they can give people gas and you
don't even realize it
again any anyone who's tried to be like
super health-conscious and lose weight
or keep your calories down and you've
gone to sugar free versions this is a
lot of the times what they've used or
again sugar substitutes etc not
high-intensity sweetener so those are
those are quite different another fun
fact about sorbitol that you may not
know actually is it's it can be used as
rocket fuel like legit rocket fuel so
for some reason it's pretty easy to to
combust well obviously it's pretty
simple but they combine it with I think
like sucrose or something like that and
do something weird and blow it up and it
can actually be as rocket fuel
alright other thing another reason why I
sort of it all became so popular or it
became so problematic though rather it
was because it's super acidic it
actually is thought to to rot your tree
your rot your teeth or has been shown to
unlike xylitol xylitol has the
fermentation problem but it actually
doesn't have to worry about rotting your
teeth because it's much lower in a
Sindhi we're sorry but all these high so
those are your FODMAPs
okay now we've talked about that let's
move on to our next category let's
remember though really quickly in order
to be a fiber basically what that means
is it passes through your small
intestines non digesting so in this
particular example these FODMAPs that
are actually not digesting the Annis i'm
also then called fibers right and these
would be the classic example of the
fermentable rapid fibers in this
category below we've talked about those
so now let's move on and get the
resistance arches and the other two
fibers the resistance starches are
slowly fermented and this is what
accounts over there so I'm only saying
this to say if you go looking around and
reading stuff it gets very confusing
because sometimes they'll call resistant
starch and fiber sometimes they want
same thing with other problem mats and I
wanted you understand all they're saying
is things candy sugar as well as a fiber
things can be a starch as well as a
fiber or not not all sugars or fibers
not all starch they're virus again it
has to do it is easily digested in the
small intestine or not if it doesn't it
can be called a fiber all right and
they'll also talk about that last
category of NSPS
all right so let's jump right into it
moving on then to these resistant
starches and non starchy polysaccharides
again if you're getting kind of lost on
this please check out the other
carbohydrate videos I have right break
down what all these fancy terms mean but
for now let's move on so our
carbohydrates are broken into three
categories yogurt starch and our Polly's
and the fiber so the starch is now I
need to break down a little bit further
so these are technically polysaccharides
and they come in two major forms amylose
and amylopectin so amylopectin is
exactly what you think of it in terms of
the normal starch used for energy broke
down fuel Krebs cycle etc amylose though
are called resistant starches so that's
the part of starch that can't be
digested so in other words if you eat a
potato it's not all usable starch some
percentage of the potato is amylopectin
and some protect percentage of it is a
moles the part that's amylose has to go
through not the SI has to go into the li
and be used as a resistant starch fiber
then as I just kind of explained is that
any sugar and starch or non starchy
polysaccharide that are non digestible
in the assign or at all so that's what
it means so then it would be a rapidly
fermented FODMAPs your slowly fermented
resistant starches and then you're never
fermented at all so with your non
starchy polysaccharides
things like lettuce technically there's
no there's not a lot of sugar in it but
there's almost no calories because it is
even though it's a polysaccharide
there's there's no real start so we call
them non starchy polysaccharides a kale
brach kale
it's a leafy greens or basically yes
right so these two types of starch is
getting to a little more specific about
75% or so of the starch that you digest
is this amylopectin its digestible it's
fine and the reason you can use it is
look at the chemical structure so if you
remember starch is a polysaccharide
meaning it has a whole bunch of glucose
stuck together but you see how it's not
nicely packed it's just like dominoes
and I use this analogy a lot in all in
many of the videos okay in dominus you
can only play on the pieces that are
uncovered same with physiology so in
this particular case since things are
not packed together there's a lot of
places where you could come in and
metabolize it there's access points if
things are all packed in like it's nice
tightly and square you can only start
playing on the edges and it takes a long
time to digest and by the time it gets
through your stomach it's already gone
here so you can start attacking
everywhere because there's so many
openings right if that didn't make sense
contrast it with this picture okay and
that's that amylose is non-digestible
it's about the other 25% or so the
starch is in chewy and it is really
tightly packed in straight line there's
no easy access points except for the
very ends to get in to start digesting
okay amylopectin is what you classically
think of when we think of glycogen okay
so when you use in your system it's easy
like this when you again consume it in
the sweet potato etc it's easy to digest
because of its open structure the
amylose though would be the resistant
starch okay now both of these are
important and they're needed so don't
just think amylopectin is better
amylopectin of course is better it's
been optimized for metabolism so in your
body you want to be able to use your
glycogen quickly as a very potent in
fact I would argue the most important
fuel source for exercise both the plants
would be the same thing right so they
want to have some portion of easily
metabolized usable energy
but then some poor
that are optimized for storage same
thing with you right you'd like to be
able to store your things so the
advantage of amylose is it's a lot
slower releasing in other words if you
were to eat say only amylopectin your
blood sugar would rise a lot faster than
it would if you were to eat only amylose
or is this a starch if you ate a food
that was say 80% amylose 20% amylopectin
you would have a very slow steady
release over time because it takes a
long time to break it down if you ate
something that was inverse almost
entirely amylopectin you would still
have a pretty fast rise in blood glucose
but not as fast if you ate pure
amylopectin or as fast if you ate say a
monosaccharide disaccharide or other
sugar so pros and cons to both of these
so the higher the percentage of
amylopectin in your food versus
Ambulance the less gas it makes you so
if the food you're eating that's giving
you problems okay it may be because it's
high in amylose so look up all the foods
you like and you can start to see the
percentages of all the starches of what
they actually have okay so a little bit
more on these resistant starches like I
said they because they go through the
microbiome bacteria they result in short
chain fatty acids and this is a straight
from Wikipedia you can go look that up
and you can look at other where we here
are some common food examples you can
give some supplements that sell these
things that come in as usually waxy
mazes but you can also do things like
green bananas as I mentioned oats are
typically high and a little bit of of
all these things and so because of that
they have that in fact if you remember
like in the 80s we've always been told
they're ultra very Hardy oatmeal is very
good oatmeal is not the same as eating
safe bread and you've probably wondered
like why and this is exactly why because
they have some percentage of resistant
and non resistant starches frozen peas
will do the same thing for you of course
as well lentils and everyone's favorite
cold pasta so if you make pasta and then
you put it in the refrigerator you eat
it the next day cold it's actually gone
from a very fast releasing starch into a
slow releasing
resistant starch for a bunch of reasons
that are important right now so
I said cold potatoes is you could if you
made like white russet potatoes and then
put them cold native the next day would
be the same thing cold pizza probably
same thing etc okay so fun stuff to play
with great stuff to have before bed as
well we've really enjoyed it there so
the go into these fibers then a little
bit more now that we've kind of covered
resistant starches fibers are usually
categories into one of two things are
either soluble or insoluble okay now if
they're soluble which means what well
they're soluble they dissolve in water
that's really all it means
so insoluble means the opposite right so
you'll know really quickly if you have a
soluble fiber if you put it in water it
makes a gelatin kind of thing common
examples in Ulan one we've already
talked about yeah classic soluble fiber
pectin raffinose and psyllium okay we'll
talk more about psyllium in a second the
insoluble ones don't dissolve in water
of course and that's stuff like
cellulose go look up that you'll
immediately recognize what that is waxes
and these resistant starches now most
foods have a combination of both but of
course some have a little bit more of
one than the other so look into those
food items if you'd like some other fun
facts about soluble versus insoluble so
the soluble ones help with glucose in
that they do they delay the release time
so in other words if you or just say
have some candy or a donut or Bob okay
just like a pixie stick and you have
something with a ton of sugar we know
that that will result a very fast
increase in blood glucose however if you
Col ingest that with a soluble fiber it
will slow down the release so this is
one of my many tricks if you need to to
have your nuggets of size or fast spikes
and blood glucose if that's desire for
whatever reason it's a congestive a
soluble fiber okay it it has the same
effect or similar effect with
cholesterol regulations so for a bunch
of reasons including bile absorption so
what soluble fibers do is they reduce
the bowel reabsorption so that means
your liver kind of has to get its
cholesterol fixed from the blood and so
it starts pulling cholesterol out of the
blood metabolizing
there rather than getting it from your
food which then of course reduces your
blood cholesterol and this is why for so
many years people have said things like
hope mill is actually good for your
heart or other various forms of
carbohydrates are good for your
cholesterol this is exactly what they're
talking about and they're definitely
right right so that's a good thing some
of the fibers also then slow digestion
um so they moved her way really slow
through the digestive tract but because
of that the increased a tiny so you feel
full because your body's been the
sensation hey don't worry about it we
got stuff in here or backed up slowly
track down so it's another reason to
have a good amount of soluble fiber in
your diet you'll feel full for longer
most of it is fermented in the large
intestines into these searching fatty
acids and thus we call them prebiotics
so they again they not probe extra
prebiotics they feed and fuel the good
bacteria and keep them alive common
foods of soluble fibers oats and barley
Xand and most basically all fruit even
avocados which is still the fruit but
people love to talk about all the fiber
and avocados and this is what they're
talking about chia seeds other seeds
lentils carrots almonds etc etc can look
up a lot of foods that are soluble
fibers any soluble base could be
opposite it tends to be called nature's
broom because it kind of sweeps things
through if you will
so if soluble fiber kind of slows
digestion insoluble does the opposite
and it kind of runs through the system
and it takes anything in there along
with it because it attracts water
alright just continues to bring water
into the digestive tract which increases
bulk in your stomach and it's often to
your stool because you put a lot of
water in there but because that it
decreases GI time in other words it goes
through fast and keeps you regular if
you want and so you don't want to have
just insoluble or soluble in fact I'll
talk about the problems if your ratios
get off here you want a little bit of
Bowl because they have specific
advantages and most of your insoluble
fibers with the exception of resistant
starches really can't be fermented so
these are the typical ones that go
through your system
non digest
classic example here cellulose which
I've mentioned a lot of times and that's
in legumes seeds root vegetables
vegetables any vegetable in the cabbage
family is going to have a ton of this
stuff and then anything with high-end
brands sweet and Cort brand skins of
fruits and vegetables tend to have a lot
of insoluble fiber and things like that
so if you want a quick trick tip on how
to figure out if you're looking at a
food item and you don't want to go to
Wikipedia or can't look it up for some
reason you want to figure out if it has
some more soluble or insoluble fiber in
it a quick way to do that is just to
imagine or actually put it in water just
run a thought experiment if it turns
into mesh its soluble right if it's not
it's insoluble so you can imagine what
happens if you put oatmeal in water it
turns and that gelatin stuff absorbs
what about celery
well celery ain't gonna do nothing in
water and so you know it's an insoluble
fiber but in getting that's what you
very good confuse just think soluble
that's what it means right does it
dissolve in water you can imagine
putting broccoli and water ain't gonna
do anything so it's heavy in the
insoluble but if you put a banana in
water it's gonna mesh up right because
it is soluble so that helped a little
bit and as I mentioned before cooking
and chewing dramatically alter the
functionality of all these carbs and
these fibers so if you're having an
issue with something but and you don't
want to take out of your diet or you
can't just change the way you prepared
chop it more blend it cook it chew it
more yeah weird novel right chew your
food it matters shocking right so a
couple of other things to pay attention
to or that you might want to know about
fiber is we can categorize them as
soluble or insoluble but we can also
categorize them by kind of have a
function and that would mean we would
call them either fermentable or bulking
or viscous fibers and so fermentable
fibers things like resisteth starch and
inulin would go to this category they
feed the bacteria they do the whole
large intestine thing they metabolize
industry chain fatty acids like we've
been talking about right and this is why
inulin was one of those FODMAPs and
we've talked about resistant starch
corner but bulking fighters like
psyllium and cellulose
absorb water promote regularity but they
can't be broken down so psyllium is
Biscay Metamucil right that's the thing
if you've ever taken Metamucil to get
you going through that's why and in fact
it's actually so good because it's a
bulking fiber and it's a viscous fiber
so it thickens your feces it promote
brings water in and it makes you poop
really really really quickly and that's
because you can't ferment it you can't
digest it you can't use any of it for
energy it goes right through so
beta-glucans and pectin it's like I've
also talked about thickened feces they
boast they blunt your postprandial sugar
responses in lipid absorption like I
just got them talking about so if you
are one who wants to really keep your or
lower your blood cholesterol levels or
you want to manage someone say with type
2 diabetes really make sure they get a
lot of these viscous fibers in which is
basically going to come from a lot of
vegetables and a lot of raw ones and
that's going to really help those
situations annual and resistant starch
not as much response from those things
alright everyone let's finish up all
this part and flash in this talk with
some practical applications so you can
understand what to do just a little bit
so you may be thinking to yourself okay
I got it
FODMAPs versus starches and fibers all
make me fart a bunch therefore I should
eliminate them from my diet or at least
significantly reduce them not so fast
look a couple of reasons you don't want
to do this number one everybody knows
really potent and rancid gas isn't
aphrodisiac in some countries so just
throwing that out there may ruin your
sex life anyways more importantly these
are actually generally considered to be
good things for you for a couple of
reasons number one it keeps your colon
healthy in fact it looks like right now
arguably the number one predictor of
colon cancer is fiber intake so people
that eat and consume a lot of fiber
particularly the ones that move quickly
through their keep the colon healthy and
they keep it from getting cancer so you
really want to have a lot of this or at
least sufficient numbers of amounts of
this in your diet number two it keeps
these good quote-unquote bacteria alive
inhale
the more recent studies are actually
showing a pretty good amount of health
benefits coming from those short chain
fatty-acids in other parts of your body
now we have a ton to learn about that
and so I'm just gonna keep it kind of
soft on here for now
there's also it also limits the impact
of blood sugar slow over these sort of
we talked about obvious one and then
number five here people often confuse
and use this as ammunition to sell low
carbohydrate or flawed mat diets under
the guy'll that these things actually
then cause inflammation Crohn's disease
irritable bowel syndrome or a whole host
of things and so let me be clear there
is no strong scientific evidence at all
that these foods cause those problems
look at the logic man I have IBS
I have gut upsets I have constant
farting I take out FODMAPs farting goes
away some it gets better therefore those
foods cause those problems no not
necessarily those things when you remove
them remove the symptom right but
something else is causing that and so
you really want to be careful of making
claims and I've seen us a ton that these
things cause inflammation o gluten
causes inflammation no probably not
not in most people all right wheat
causes inflammation the gut no no no no
no they don't
okay this is very very different from
from what's actually happening so don't
confuse relieving the symptom with the
actual Cosma so if you are having gut
problems you should maybe try to remove
these if it goes away that gives you
evidence now you need to go figure out
why your stomach isn't digesting say
fructose like it should be and then
explore whether or not that's a fixable
problem or not I'll give you a hint so
it's coming what's the time it is
sometimes it's not okay but don't
confuse these and that people say you
want things therefore if fiber causes
you too far you shouldn't eat fiber
that's complete nonsense so what are
some of these major common causes of GI
distress is what I'm calling a
gastrointestinal distress it could be a
couple things number one too many
carbohydrates
in fact if you watch any my other videos
on performance you'll see that
carbohydrates are very very very helpful
at any type of endurance activity longer
than like a minute okay and in fact the
research shows it you're gonna
performance is gonna go up significantly
and the amount that we typically
recommend is something like sixty to
eighty grams of carbohydrate per hour
and you typically want to split that up
with a dosages so you have a lot 15
grams every 15 or 20 minutes or so so
you do that three or four times and
you're there however the major downside
of carbohydrate during performance is it
causes a lot of people to go sprinting
towards the Porta Potty in the middle of
a marathon and they shift their brains
up and it's awful or just bubbly guts
farting I know that several people
during like ultra marathons that I've
worked with one girl Nicole in bad water
classic was just like I can't have any
more carbohydrates my guts is blown up
and that's a very legitimate phenomenon
and they're not they don't have gut
microbiome issues they disaffected they
have a huge bolus of carbohydrates and
so that number tends to be anywhere
between like honestly even as low as 60
or 70 up to like 120 in terms of how
much it takes to disrupt somebody's good
and so that could be it you may just not
be able to give them as many
carbohydrates at once and so typically I
like to stay below 100 grams per hour
and unless I know that they don't have
any issues with that and you just need
to be careful of what types of
carbohydrates they're giving them
another major cause is any of these
fibers that we earn a these foods we
just talked about it's just a use you
went up too quickly on them so let's
just make this a number say you were
eating 50 of these total and you also
knew went to 150 it's not the fact that
150 is bad for you it's the fact that
you tripled your intake of these things
and you didn't give your body time to
digest so a classic example this is if
you eat a lot of beans frequently beans
don't give you very much gas however if
you never eat beans and you eat a giant
burrito with with black beans and kidney
beans in it you're definitely gonna fart
your face out all right yes that's a
phrase it's a scientific term for ting
your face up so again it's not the fact
that the beans are bad for you and it's
the fact that you took something that
you did not have a digestive
times four or the microbiome to handle
and it blew up a little bit so if you
want to be able to eat more of these
foods for whatever reason just slowly
increase their mouths over time please
please friends if you're giving somebody
else a diet if you give me it to them
pay attention to this I promise you you
will get immediate feedback on this one
if you're like whoo
I went from never being on a diet or not
being on a diet and last four months I
followed this to the tea and I am
bloated and gassy and feel awful all day
that's your fault you got to look at
their die and go okay they're used to
having seven grams of fiber a day and
now I'm gonna give them 40 what he
expects gonna happen all right they're
either gonna knock poop for three days
or poop every three minutes or their
stomachs gonna be distended out to here
right they're gonna look like well put
up they're gonna tear so we just pay
attention that okay you can get them to
40 if that's the number you want just go
slowly and then number three here they
could have some innate sensitivity or
allergy and so there are tests you can
get al cat tests that honestly they're
terrible food sensitivity and allergy
test it's a really shoddy science at
this point I have used it before with
some really good success but if you get
these things and they come back and say
hey you're highly highly severely
sensitive dude ba ba ba ba ba moderately
sensitive to this and lowly just just
interpret that was extreme caution right
the science is very poor in these areas
extremely poor so it could be useful but
be careful literally I get examples
already given you lactose things like
that right gluten or not gluten right
we've had issues with athletes with this
before where they thought they were
sensitive to gluten because of stomach
issues so they've gone gluten free
gluten substitutes and actually found
out that those were far worse gone back
to gluten and things got way better
right so you never know the next two
categories are a little bit different
though there could be some sort of
damage to the stomach lining you can
kind of look in the leaky gut if you
will in that and that's a real potential
issue or you could be what I call
microbiota problems so this could be
things like an imbalance of bacteria and
a large intestines and another one word
though
be very very very careful we still don't
know what this even really means here's
what I can tell you and I can I'll give
you a story about this in a second if
you are really out of whack here it has
real problems everywhere but anything
passed like crazy out of whack we really
don't know so we're learning give us 10
years give us at least five years but
right now the science on what it means
to have good or what the healthy ones
are what your ratio should be nobody
really knows what they're doing here
we're really just guessing outside of
some extreme problems a one that is a
little bit more document of those called
SIBO
Zeebo which is small intestinal
bacterial overgrowth so we've talked
about how those bacteria should be in
your large intestine for the most part
if some of those go creeping down and
get into your small intestines or you
get things like yeast overgrowth these
can cause all kinds of problems and you
just got to cancel that out clear it out
and you end up feeling tremendously
better so SIBO is very real and it can
actually be easily tested these top two
categories they're simply as a result of
you had too much carbohydrate these are
not really representative of intolerance
typically or got actual problems you
just need to you know evolve into those
are gradually progressed but the last
three here can result in autoimmune
responses as well so common examples of
things like this it could cause
flare-ups of eczema or psoriasis it
could cause pain achiness hep but like
all kinds of stuff associate with
autoimmune and that's because of this we
do know as crappy and shoddy as of
sciences there is a very strong
relationship between the gut microbiome
the bacteria and everything in your body
right some people have used this to
explain the quote-unquote gut instinct
but whatever but we do know that
something like 80% of immune system is
generated from the gut a vast majority
of like your serotonin which makes you
sleep comes from the gut and again we
got a lot to work out here really be
careful of like the functional medicine
people and a lot of other practitioners
they abuse the crap out of this stuff
they overshoot and over speak way too
far but there's clearly something here
there
there okay it's just murky right now but
it's something is there okay there's a
strong relationship between a lot a lot
of things in your function again your
hormones sleep regulation mood all this
stuff
something's going on the gut so if you
have something wrong in your gut and
then you eat something that causes that
the flare-up or it gives you problems
you can see issues arise throughout the
body and it is a problem in your gut in
fact actually studied just came out this
week showing that that actually can get
into your nose and that causes nasal
information that explains some reasons
of why people have a hard time breathing
through their nose sometimes one study
just came out don't get overly excited
but it's pretty cool right more this
lactobacillus stuff is is looking so I
want to show you once one story on this
so this is my friend Bryan Callen you
may know him he's a super famous actor
but and Bryan's talked about this openly
on a numerous podcast so I can feel free
to share this but Bryan came to me a
couple years ago and he had really bad
psoriasis his whole life he had a huge
outbreak so I worked with him for a
while and eventually I figured out yeah
I'm pretty sure if something's going on
in your gut so I reached out to my
friend Dan garner who's a lot better at
that stuff than I am Dan called in some
gut microbiome testing we got it back we
figured out he actually did have some
bacterial overgrowth and some some real
disruptions going on there so we Dan put
him on a 90-day protocol that's specific
types of probiotics and prebiotics and
some other things we limited because
this is testosterone goes down we got
all that stuff fixed sleep got better
psoriasis went away he's talked about
this openly it's been a couple of years
now and it hasn't come back so psoriasis
is not one things you can cure because
it is autoimmune but as long as you keep
it in check it is stayed away and it was
massive I mean if you're a fan of his he
talked about it a lot prior to come
getting to me he was complaining about
it a ton on his podcast and shows and
stuff and they were making fun of
constantly balling him for a long time
and he did a lot of crazy stuff with
night shades and all this like super
popular if you google around stuff we
finally came to me and I'm like no
instead of covering a symptom here like
let's go up to the cons that was a clear
case of the cause now
one thing I'll pause on this one
everyone thinks say every time I have a
problem I have a gut microbiome issue
this was one case when it was true I
honestly say 95 percent of the people
have come to me with that it was not
their gut microbiome was just fine as we
don't know so but he had a whole bunch
of symptoms and we went through a lot of
stuff again we worked for several months
on things before I could triage and
diagnose I actually I do think you have
and I brought it up actually wasn't him
so anyways Brian looks fantastic tell
him how sexy and pretty he looks now
with his clear skin so anyways the gut
microbiome is a really cool place we got
a couple of studies going on right now
with the gut microbiome that are a
pretty badass so you can look into stuff
but I want to show you a couple of
things like fecal transplants are
actually a legitimate thing so there is
some evidence where you can take say the
poop from somebody else get it kind of
their stomach put it in your stomach and
people see some pretty impressive
improvements and things like obesity and
health and again most of this is
overblown but there is some very
legitimate science behind some of these
things and you can also do stuff like
this where this is one clinical trial
that Boston Children's Hospital did
where they can you can get poop in a
pill if you will and take it and adjust
it that way and really what they're
doing is you're trying to fix this gut
microbiome it's a very very popular and
hot topic and physiology research in
fact my friends couple my friends
Timmy Bagley and Gregor Sookie I've done
this a lot and they've shown that the
gut microbiome is actually related to
your vo2 max they've also shown that it
changes acutely so they did a really
cool study with a world class ultra
marathon runner and showed a dramatic
change of the gut microbiome at the end
of the ultra marathon there's some
additional evidence that all types of
exercise can alter your microbiome
endurance exercise we were doing a trial
like I said now on strength training
whether or not that does it we of course
know food consumption fiber and take all
this stuff alters it so we are really
swimming in the dark with the gut
microbiome but there's something cool
here we just really don't know what
we're doing this is really what I want
to get so
to give you some very final thoughts and
and specific recommendations let's go so
most people are gonna generally
recommend that you consume some in the
neighborhood of 14 to 16 grams of fiber
per day per thousand calories you ingest
so if you eat 2,000 calories a day 30 30
to 35 grams of fiber per day or
fantastic if you look at your dietary
recall on MyFitnessPal or something
you're at 40 or 50 you probably don't
feel so great if you're at 6 again you
are probably pooping every third or
fourth day it's not a good thing you
should be going at least once per day
anyway yeah if you have too much fiber
this could cause diarrhea could cause
bloating and gas but it's really good
for your colon health and say tidy on
the other end of spectrum if you don't
have enough fiber you can also be
constipated it could be bloating a gassy
but you increase the nutrient extraction
so I'll give you an example of this of
this in a second but it highlights one
of my favorite topics called hormesis I
would point you to my crew CEO he's
talked about this at nauseam in a bunch
of different areas but you don't want to
have too much of something in your body
you don't wanna have too little of it
finding where you are and that curve is
really really important so say you're an
example of your when you're cutting
weight or you're trying to lose weight
you're calorically restricted one
advantage of having higher fiber that
makes you feel full is you aren't as
hungry anymore and so you can keep the
same exact calorie count go up and the
fiber that makes you feel full soluble
right and you're like wow my hunger
pangs aren't nearly as bad so that's a
little so just by looking at their food
you may switch out one food item for
another food item nothing else is
different and there aren't as hungry
although the advantage of that though
because it moves slower again through
there is you're also going to extract
more nutrients and so when you're in a
caloric deficit
you're not eating as much food so you're
not bringing in as many cat as many
vitamins minerals and phytochemicals
into your mouth but if you slow down the
transit time in other words keeping your
stomach longer that gives you a longer
timeframe to pull the nutrients that you
do consume out of it if you think
about this evolutionary earlier this is
a huge advantage right if you're you
don't know when your next meal is coming
you don't want things you'd be eating
and pooping things out five minutes you
want to be getting everything possible
out of that food before you poop it out
and if that means you walk around a
little bit bloated and constipated were
the exchange to not die on the other end
of the spectrum if you're eating too
much then it's gonna fly out really
really really quickly
okay so again there's pros and cons to
both of them but like I just to really
clarify that the downside of that
super-high like really slow transit time
thing is it looks like it's not great
for your colon health so you could have
potential problems there so my
recommendation with fiber is keep it
with these where these numbers are
unless you're really in specific times
if you're in a lot of calorie high
caloric surplus
I typically reduce fiber intake again
because now your stomach you're trying
to X have 1015 percent extra calories
all that fiber then really starts to pay
dividends if things go through a little
bit quicker through your system it's
okay because you're eating more total
food and that reduces GI distress if
you're the opposite right you favor the
other direction if you've been in any my
classes or watched any of my videos you
know that this is how I honestly like to
approach nutrition supplementation
performance and all real thinking is
it's not what's right what's wrong it's
what's the advantage what's a
disadvantage then depending on your
situation
apply appropriately so there are some
times when I might go down as low as
like 8 grams of fiber per thousand
calories or I might go as high as 20
all right depending on the situation
that bran if that's way too much
thinking for you if you just eat a
variety of whole real foods you're
probably going to land right in this
number you can be just fine where people
have to pay real attention to this again
is if they're really high in calories
really low in calories or most of their
food comes processed and packaged a lot
of times what happens when we processed
food is we strip the the nutrients the
vitamins the minerals and the fiber away
now some of them are fortified so they
put the vitamins back in
but they don't put the fiber back in so
you could be eating a lot of things that
are typically high in fiber like plants
and breads and pastas and things like
that but if they're enriched and they
have had the fiber removed you have a
very high carbohydrate diet but you
don't have a very high fiber diet and
therefore you have to get with edit out
of fiber things
so again just eat real whole food for
most of your food or a lot of it and
you're going to be just fine with fiber
for the most part okay let's put you to
the test here some active learning I'm
going to give you a couple of examples
of someone eating a healthy diet quote
having problems and there's somebody
eating an unhealthy diet having problems
and I want to see if you can figure out
what's actually going on so here's our
case of our broccoli so in other words
imagine somebody comes in and says ok
that's right I'm that's it I'm turning
my life around I'm having a healthy diet
and they go from eating pizza stuff all
day to really high quality Whole Foods
like I'm recommending they get a lot of
vegetables they get pounding on the
asparagus and the broccoli and cabbage
and collard greens and just everything
well what would be the symptom that they
would come here with what would they say
to you where you go oh I know what's
happening what they feel what they feel
diarrhea where they feel bloating or
they feel gas would they be constipated
what would it be what would you do about
it what's their problem what do they
have too much up that's right it's the
insoluble fiber right so in this
particular case you might want to say
hey look you're eating too much broccoli
you don't need a pound you don't need a
kilo gram of broccoli a day let's reduce
insoluble fiber or fiber in total or
reduce insoluble and add in more soluble
fiber right and so you may be hurting
your own gut and causing your you all
kinds of problems of pain discomfort
because you're trying to eat
quote-unquote too healthy and so really
be careful about that maybe you need to
take out some of that broccoli and added
back in a piece of toast you may feel a
little bit better so what was the answer
then they're actually gone playing would
be they probably feel super bloated
that's very common
again the cruciferous vegetables very
often results in excess employed alright
what about that one someone comes to you
what would be their complaint man I mean
pizza and fries and eat the the meal the
cafeterias all day you probably want to
reduce their soluble fiber and increase
their insoluble fiber or just increase
in soluble fiber and the complaint that
they would have would not be bloating so
much although maybe but most likely it's
the fact that they are either really
irregular yeah I poop twice today and
then I didn't went four days without it
and I'm just I'm all over the map and or
they have like mild very mild diarrhea
or just really sloppy poop
they're like man I went the bathroom
it's just a mess in there that's
probably because you don't have enough
insoluble fiber yeah because remember
soluble fiber makes water makes gel we
get a lot of gelatin in there but not a
lot of structure right now it's not as
simple as that
but hopefully you're sort of thinking
through what you've learned a little bit
so some potential solutions you could
come up with if you're having gut
district problems in here right just
disruptions disturbances there you go
you could maybe say hey look maybe if I
have more pre or probiotic supplements
or I eat more foods with these in them
maybe that could work or maybe I could
take digestive enzymes and both of those
things are very valid solutions so the
prebiotic probiotic side would increase
those gut bacteria spur typically in the
in the colon and you could tackle that
way or you can simply say hey I know
that I'm gonna have some beans tonight
and I know that has raffinose and I know
raffinose needs an enzyme called a gal
to produce it therefore I'm gonna go to
the store and buy some digestive enzymes
which is a whole bunch of a go and that
will actually probably work the downside
of these things right now it looks like
any supplementation or pre or probiotics
is extremely transient so two or three
days maybe week after you stop taking
that supplement they're gone and that's
generally because unless the bacteria
you're taking have an ecological
advantage once they get in there
they're gonna die out survival of the
fittest right it's natural selection so
unless they have some survival advantage
when they get in there as soon as you
stop taking them they're gonna get wiped
out again and that's typically what we
see happen so they're mostly only
effective when you keep taking them
we're also clueless in this area I've
already talked about this but we really
don't know what we're going on what's
going on with I've got microbiome so we
definitely don't know what's going on in
terms of supplementation at the most
part we're really monkeying around way
around this stuff and so because that
the prescriptions are too big there are
so many different types nobody knows
what type to take how much what
combinations who should get what it's a
lot of guesswork so some people have a
better understanding here than others
but it's still a tremendous amount of
guesswork so it's a possible way to help
you understand but I don't see this as a
long-term viable solution digestive
enzymes are the same problem probably
fairly transient you got to take them
basically when you eat the food so you
got to take this pill remember to eat it
you know with your meal which is not
that hard but not always feasible we're
all so clueless here there's a ton of
different enzymes you need and they're
actually too specific so if you're
having a high-protein meal you need to
take digestive enzymes that break that
or proteolytic right the breakdown
protein if you're gonna have ralph
unless you take a go if you're having a
different time if it's gonna be so all
you need to take that if it's gonna be
only go set you get so you get have like
all either by like a digestive enzyme
pack with like all kinds of them in
there but then you don't even know if
you have that much and you're taking
much once you don't need cuz you really
want to get a go or you have to get like
bottles it okay not that difficult if
you really want to like my god my
stomach is blowing up every time I eat
kale what the hell let's see if this
works
great but I don't see this as major
long-term solutions and maybe I'll wear
this differently we just need a lot more
information in these areas right so
there's a lot to go here I think the
probably the most salient solution I'll
provide to you is lives and and I'm
shocked they even have to say this but I
can't tell you how many times I've heard
this if you're going to for example give
somebody fiber or give somebody
carbohydrates during competition
please God please ooze please whoever it
is a you care to try it in practice
first don't give somebody a sucrose
fructose punny electrolyte solution in
competition that they have never done in
practice you might blow them to pieces
right they might set a PR from all 0 to
5 and then spend 20 minutes in the
don't do things with their
stomach that you know how potential
digestive issues that they've never
tried I always go to practice I always
go to sparring I always go to these
things
try the cocktail but I think we want to
use in the competition or right before
or whatever
we tried multiple times I have them
drink them and practice we do it 8 tons
that I can figure out what their gut can
handle do not do this stuff without
trying it first it sounds ridiculous I'd
have to say it but I have to it's super
calm right so practice your pre or mid
fueling strategy before your
competitions this will help a tremendous
amount and then lastly here I've alluded
to this but use the concept of hormesis
and I've got a 5 minute video on that if
you want to go look it up but for
example which is better for you brown
rice or white rice well the answer is
you're in paying attention it depends so
typically what happens as I've said with
processed food that means the brand or
the fiber on the outside of the coating
of the wheat for example has been
removed and they put the B vitamins and
iron back in but not the fiber so this
would be maybe say a processed white
rice the bran the brown one has the
outside post-exercise your post
competition I might actually use the
processed version why because I don't
want the fiber
why because it slows down how quickly it
gets in bloodstream if I want to
maximize rehydration I want to maximize
glycogen resynthesis I want to go with
the faster releasing glucose so post
exercise I'll go white rice at night
before off days whatever I might go
brown rice because I know it releases
slower so I won't get a glucose spike
and so again I can't emphasize enough
folks pros and cons it's not about
better or worse it's not about well
rice is better because it's healthier
not for an athlete let's use what we
understand about physiology biochemistry
and nutritional sciences to our
advantage
don't give your athletes a huge amount
of fiber immediately post exercise if
you need to maximize recovery if you've
got four days before the competing again
it probably doesn't matter but if you're
leaving and going to another practice or
you've got two more practices the next
day which I almost always deal with with
the athletes I work with you really need
to pay attention when you're giving them
fiber and when you're not you want them
to feel full and you want them to feel
hungry so they'll actually get enough
food in what do you want okay so that's
it hopefully you learned a lot about why
you fought so much maybe I'll make
another video sometime probably not
though and why your farts smells so
sneakier or they're not this was a lot
of work this took me a lot longer than I
was anticipating it so hopefully this
made you smile quite a bit you can send
this to your friends and family and
let's let's make this thing go viral I
want the whole world to know why you
fart so much and what you can do about
it if you have that because like I said
everybody loves a good fart but it has
to be at the right time in the right
place no one must be farting when they
don't want to fart and no one wants to
be a place where they could let one out
and they just can't why whatever
happened but hopefully you're
appreciating all the effort I put in
these things and if you are you know how
to repay me alright so go out there have
fun tell your friends this at your next
party
yes
[Music]